A Guide to the Basl family papers, 1935-1998
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Basl family papers, 1935-1998
The Library of Virginia
50557, 50826
.9 cu. ft. and 2 boxes
Basl family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jim Basl.
Biographical Information
Rose Popek was born 30 August 1919 in Richmond, Virginia, to Vaclav Popek and Katherine Prastil Popek, Czechoslovakian immigrants. Her father was a gardener and the family lived in Richmond until she was 6 years old, then moved to Hanover County, Virginia. Rose Popek graduated from Washington Henry High School in Hanover County in 1936 and attended Smithdeal Massey Business School. Popek worked for the Commonwealth of Virginia in the unemployment commission. After her marriage to Joseph Basl in 1947, Rose Basl moved to Prince George County, Virginia, working as a clerk in an insurance agency. The Basls had two children. After her husband's death in 1971, Rose Basl worked as a clerk in a realty and in an insurance agency, then for the city of Petersburg, Virginia.
James Joseph Basl was born 19 July 1949 to Joseph Basl (d. 1971) and Rose Popek Basl (1919-) in Petersburg, Virginia. He attended Petersburg Public High School and the University of Virginia, from where he graduated with a BA in 1971. Basl earned a Master's of Business Administration from Virginia Commonwealth University in 1978. After graduation, Basl worked in banking. He now lives in Midlothian, Chesterfield County, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1935-1998, of the Basl family of Chesterfield and Hanover Counties, and Petersburg and Richmond, Virginia, consisting of ads, correspondence, diaries, essays, exams, guides, licenses, membership cards, notes, poems, programs, reports, songs, stories, and other papers of Rose Popek Basl (1919-) and her son James J. Basl (1949-).
Contents List
- Rose Popek Basl papers, 1935-1998., Extent: 1 box. (Box 1)
  Papers, 1935-1998, of Rose Popek Basl (1919-) of Hanover County and Petersburg, Virginia, consisting of information on Washington-Henry High School in Hanover County, Christmas poems, a driver's license, a Girl Scout membership card, notes on Czechlosovakia, a song sheet, information on Hanover Town, an ad for fishing rods and tackle, a business guide and information sheet for Pungo and Sandbridge in Virginia Beach, Virginia. Collection also includes programs for the Washington-Henry High School senior class play, Man of La Mancha performed at the Barksdale Theatre, and a performance by pianist Rudolph Firkunsy. Papers also include correspondence, 1988-1998, from Juanice Ford of Redondo Beach, California, and Diane Popek of Czechlosovakia, discussing personal and family news, and reminiscing about Virginia.
  The Washington-Henry Gazette, newspapers for Washington-Henry High School in Hanover County, Virginia, have been transferred to the Library of Virginia Newspaper Project. The issues run from 1933 to 1935.
  - Correspondence, 1988-1998. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, programs, cards, licenses, notebooks, business guides, and miscellaneous papers, 1935-1998. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- James J. Basl papers, 1962-1990., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  Papers, 1962-1990, of James J. Basl of Chesterfield County and Petersburg and Richmond, Virginia, consisting of compositions, diaries, essays, exams, poems, programs, reports, stories, and other papers from Basl's time as a student in the Petersburg Public School system and as a student at the University of Virginia. Papers highlight his interests in literature, history, sociology, and computers, and contain essays, stories, and poems written by Basl while a student. Diaries include descriptions of his stays at Seashore State Park (now First Landing State Park); papers also cover his extracurricular activies in campus politics at Virginia and his work in the banking industry.
  Two issues of the Cavalier Daily (15 September 1967 and 28 October 1968) have been transferred to the Library of Virginia Newspaper project. Copies of these issues can be found in on film 2563.
  - Seashore State Park (First Landing State Park) diaries, 1962-1963, undated. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1967. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1968. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Diary, ca. 1966-1969. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Diary sections, undated. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - My Autobiography. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Absurd in the Philosophy of Albert Camus, English 8A paper. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Can We Dissent? English 9 paper, 2 June 1967. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Onlooker, (F. Scott Fitzgerald), 11th grade term paper. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Electronic Digital Computer. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The World of Sherlock Holmes, English 1, section 3C, 13 May 1968. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Class paper on the 1920s, HIUS 52 paper, undated. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - A White Southerner Attempts to Come to Grips with the Black Panthers, HIUS 82, 8 May 1970. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Final exam, Sociology 4. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Draft of letter, etc., concerning the Democratic primary race for gubernatorial nomination, 1969. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - University of Virginia student strike, 1970. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Jefferson Literary and Debating Society draft letter (University of Virginia). (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - A Study of the Infromation Systems Software Procurement and Contracting Process at a Commercial Bank, August 1977. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Professional papers, banking, 1983-1989. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Birth account, undated. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letter, undated. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Stories, essays, compositions, circa 1960s. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Poems, titled. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Poems, untitled. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General notes on coursework, etc. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Progressive Party (University of Virginia). (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - University of Virginia Graduation Exercises, 6 June 1971. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University Commencement Program, 1978. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Italy trip, 1971. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - University of Virginia syllabus and honor pledge, ca. 1968. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Raven Society (University of Virginia). (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Invitation to the Eighth Annual Restoration Ball of the University of Virginia, 8 May 1971. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Songs, poems, writings, etc., by others, including cheers and songs for Petersburg High School. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Printed material: Ninth Annual Central District Basketball Tournament; open house card for School of Engineering at the University of Virginia; Rapier cover; Proposal for an Information Retrieval System for U.Va. Students and Faculty; and An Open Letter to Bankers Everywhere from the Boston Phoenix, 1965-1990. (Box 2, Folder 22)